chapter 15 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public domain Black Beauty by Anna
Su chapter 15 The Old Osa After this it was decided by my
master and mistress to pay a visit to some friends who lived about 46 miles
from our home, and James was to drive them. The first day we traveled 32 miles.
There were some long, heavy hills, but James drove so carefully and
thoughtfully that we were not at all harassed. He never forgot to put on the
break as we went downhill, nor to take it off at the right place. He kept our feet
on the smoothest part of the road, and if the uphill was very long, he set the
carriage wheels a little across the road, so as not to run back, and gave us a
breathing. All these little things help a horse very much, particularly if he gets
kind words into the bargain. We stopped once or twice on the road, and just as
the sun was going down we reached the town where we were to spend the night. We
stopped at the principal hotel, which was in the marketplace it was a very large
one; we drove under an archway into a long yard, at the further end of which
were the stables and Coach houses Two ostlers came to take us out. The head
oser was a pleasant, active little man, with a crooked leg, and a yellow striped
waste coat I never saw a man unbuckle harness as quickly as he did, and with a
pat and a good word he led me to a long
stable, with six or eight stalls in it, and two or three horses. The other man
brought Ginger; James stood by while we were rubbed down and cleaned. I never was
cleaned so lightly and quickly as by that little old man. When he had done James stepped up
and felt me over, as if he thought I could not be thoroughly done, but he
found my coat as clean and smooth as silk. “Well,” he said, “I thought I was pretty
quick, and our John quicker still, but you do beat all I ever saw for being quick
and thorough at the same time.” “Practice makes perfect,” said the
crooked little Osa and would be a pity if it didn't 40 years' practice, and not
perfect that would be a pity; and as to being quick, why, bless you! that is only a
matter of habit; if you get into the habit of being quick it is just as easy
as being slow; easier, I should say; in fact it doesn't agree with my health to
be hulking about over a job twice as long as it need take. Bless you! I
couldn't whistle if I crawled over my work as some folks do! You see, I have
been about horses ever since I was 12 years old, in hunting stables, and racing
stables; and being small you see, I was jockey for several years; but at the
Goodwood you see, the turf was very slippery and my poor lburg got a fall,
and I broke my knee so of course I was
of no more use there. But I could not live without horses, of of course I
couldn't, so I took to the hotels. And I can tell you it is a downright pleasure
to handle an animal like this well bred well-mannered well cared for bless ye! I
can tell how a horse is treated. Give me the handling of a horse for 20 minutes,
and I'll tell you what sort of groom he has had. Look at this one, pleasant, quiet,
turns about just as you want him, holds his feet up to be cleaned out, or
anything else you please to wish; then you'll find another fidgety fresh
won't move the right way, or starts across the stall, tosses up his head as
soon as you come near him, lays his ears, and seems afraid of you; or else squares
about at you with his heels. Poor things!
I know what sort of treatment they have had. If they are timid it makes them
start or shy; if they are high metal it makes them vicious or dangerous; their
tempers are mostly made when they are young. Bless you! they are like children,
train them up in the way they should go, as the good book says, and when they are
old they will not depart from it, if they have a
chance.” “I like to hear you talk,” said James, “that's the way we lay it down at
home, at our master's.” “Who is your master, young man? if
it be a proper question. I should judge he is a good one, from what I
see.” “He is Squire Gordon, of Berwick Park, the other side of the Beacon Hills,” said
James. “Ah! so, so I've heard tell of him; fine judge of horses, ain't he? the best
rider in the county.” “I believe he is,” said James, “but he
rides very little now, since the poor young master was killed.” “Ah! poor gentleman; I read all
about it in the paper at the time. A fine horse killed, too, wasn't
there?” “Yes,” said James; “he was a splendid creature, brother to this one, and just like
him.” “Pity! pity!” said the old man it was a
bad place to leap, if I remember; a thin fence at top, a steep bank down to the
stream, wasn't it? No chance for a horse to see where he is going. Now I'm for
bold riding as much as any man, but still there are some leaps that only a very
knowing old huntsman has any right to take. A man's life and a horse's life are
worth more than a fox's tail; at least, I should say they ought to
be.” During this time the other man had finished Ginger and had brought our corn,
and James and the old man left the stable together end of chapter